# Samee Arif

samee.arif@lums.edu.pk • Website • Google Scholar • Github • Huggingface

## **RESEARCH INTEREST**

My research focuses on Information & Communication Technologies for Development, Human-Computer Interaction, and Speech and Natural Language Processing. I am committed to leveraging these fields to create meaningful social impacts, particularly by enhancing accessibility and usability of technology.

## **EDUCATION**

#### **Bachelor of Science in Computer Science**

Sep 2019 - May 2023

Lahore University of Management Sciences (LUMS)

 <u>Relevant Coursework</u>: Artificial Intelligence, Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Natural Language Processing, Speech Processing, Principles and Techniques of Data Science, Computer Vision, Mathematical Foundations for Machine Learning and Data Science, Probability, Calculus II

## RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Student Counseling Chatbot | Python, Next. js, React, FastAPI, Git, Google Colab

Aug 2023 - Present

- Developing a graduate assistant tool leveraging Large Language Models (LLMs) to provide educational counselina.
- Worked on prompt engineering for LLMs.
- Implemented multimodality by integrating Automatic Speech Recognition (ASR) and Text-to-Speech (TTS) systems.

**Urdu Question-Answering** | Python, Transformers, PyTorch, Google Colab

Jan 2023 - Oct 2023

- Developed a Question-Answering corpus for the Urdu language to address the limited resources available in the domain.
- Manually evaluated Seamless M4T and Google Translator for Urdu.
- Introduced EATS a technique to preserve the answer spans in the translated context paragraphs and employed it to translate the SQuAD2.0 dataset to Urdu.
- Successfully generated 124,745 question-answer pairs and fine-tuned mBERT, XLM-RoBERTa, mT5 and LLaMA-2 on our dataset to achieve an 85.99% F1 Score and 74.56% Exact Match.
- First authored and published a research paper at LREC-Coling 2024.

## Image-to-Speech Pipeline for Urdu Language | Python

Sep 2021 - Sep 2022

- Evaluated Optical Character Recognition (OCR) models including Tesseract, EasyOCR, and Kraken on Nastaliq font
- Established a pipeline to replicate scanned images using data augmentation to generate the dataset.
- Fine-tuned GANs to map the noisy images to clean images as a pre-processing module.
- Implemented a post-processing module based on BERT, Google search engine auto-correction and conditional random fields to enhance the model accuracy.
- Trained Tesseract to achieve a 1.53% Character Error Rate and piped it with my Text-to-Speech (TTS) model.

## **WORK EXPERIENCE**

#### Research Associate | ActualAlz (LUMS)

Aug 2023 - Present

- Advisor(s): Dr. Agha Ali Raza, Dr. Ihsan Ayyub Qazi and Dr. Zafar Ayyub Qazi (LUMS).
- Working on developing a multimodal and multilingual graduate assistant tool leveraging large language models to provide educational counseling.

#### Research Assistant | CSaLT (LUMS)

Aug 2021 - May 2023

- Advisor(s): Dr. Raza (LUMS), Dr. Awais Athar (EMBL-EBI).
- Worked on image-to-speech pipeline and Urdu question-answering system.

## **Teaching Assistant** | *Machine Learning (LUMS)*

Fall 2022

 Oversaw and facilitated learning for a cohort of 149 students. Designed and administered course quizzes, assignments and a project to gauge student understanding and progress.

## **Teaching Assistant** | Computational Problem Solving (LUMS)

Fall 2021

• Managed a 93-student cohort, designed quizzes, and labs and held weekly office hours.

#### **PROJECTS**

**Speech Technologies** | Python, PyTorch, Transformers, React, FastAPI, Git

Aug 2023 - Dec 2023

- Fine-tuned Whisper and MMS ASR model, achieving a 13.01% WER. Analyzed model quality and inference time, integrated quantization for faster inference, and utilized QLoRA for efficient fine-tuning.
- Trained MMS-TTS and YourTTS, adapting a VITS TTS framework script for training.
- Created a web-based audio annotation tool providing editable transcriptions and timestamps using ASR.

#### **ConvoLense** | Python, Transformers FastAPI, Git

Aug 2023 - Sep 2023

- Evaluated speech-based (Wav2Vec2) and text-based (BERT, mT5, GPT, LLaMA) emotion classifiers.
- Used Bark to generate a synthetic conversation dataset between customer and customer service representative.
- Established a pipeline using my ASR model and LLM for emotion classification.

## **Arabic Handwriting Recognition** | Python

Jan 2023 - May 2023

- Applied transfer learning techniques to adapt the Urdu OCR model for recognizing handwritten Arabic in Naskh font.
- Utilized advanced pre-processing methods, such as skeletonization, to generate a synthetic handwritten dataset.

#### Image Captioning | Python, PyTorch, Google Colab

Jan 2023 - May 2023

 Conducted an experimental fine-tuning of Swin-Transformer on the Indiana University - Chest X-Rays dataset, exploring its application in medical image analysis.

#### Fraudulent Job Prediction | Python, Scikit-learn, Pandas Jupyter

Sep 2022 - Dec 2022

- Trained Logistic Regression, Support Vector Machine, and Random Forest classifiers to identify real versus fake
  job postings, achieving a 91% Accuracy.
- Conducted comprehensive data cleaning and exploratory data analysis on the dataset.
- Authored and published an article on Medium detailing the project's methodology and outcomes.

#### Lane Analysis for Autonomous Vehicle | Python, PyTorch, Google Colab

Sep 2022 - Dec 2022

 Created a lane-change warning system, integrating Lanenet for lane detection and YOLOv7 for vehicle detection.

#### **Learning Management System** | MongoDB, Node.js, React, Git, Trello, Postman

Jan 2022 - May 2022

• Created a platform for schools to manage online education during the pandemic.

#### Speech-based Language Classifier | Python, Scikit-learn, Jupyter

Sep 2021 - Dec 2021

- Recorded voice samples in English, Urdu, and a mix of both languages at 1600MHz.
- Developed and trained a neural network from scratch to classify speech using the recordings dataset.

FoodSwings | HTML, CSS, Bootstrap, React, Node.js, MySQL, Postman

Sep 2021 - Dec 2021

• Implemented food delivery web application.

#### Neural Network from Scratch | Python, NumPy, Jupyter

Sep 2021 - Dec 2021

Developed a feed-forward neural network from scratch using NumPy and optimized it with Numba's JIT.

## **AWARDS**

 Dean's Honour List | LUMS
 Fall 2020

 Dean's Honour List | LUMS
 Spring 2019

#### **TECHNICAL SKILLS**

Languages | Python, C/C++, SQL, JavaScript, HTML/CSS

Frameworks | React, Node.js, Next.js, FastAPI

**Developer Tools** | Git, Docker, Google Cloud Platform, VS Code, Visual Studio

Libraries | pandas, NumPy, Matplotlib, TensorFlow, PyTorch, Keras, transformers, Streamlit

## **PUBLICATIONS**

[1] Samee Arif, Sualeha Farid, Awais Athar, and Agha Ali Raza, UQA: Corpus for Urdu Question Answering. In LREC-COLING 2024 – Joint International Conference on Computational Linguistics, Language Resources and Evaluation. May 20-25, 2024, Torino (Italia). (Ranks 6th from top in Computational Linguistics)